Guide to the Morris and Adele Bergreen Albert Einstein Collection, 1919-1988
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Morris and Adele Bergreen Albert Einstein Collection
1919-1988
Einstein, Albert, 1879-1955
2.2 cubic feet (11 boxes)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Composed mainly of correspondence between Einstein and the executor of his estate, Otto Nathan. Also includes letters from Elsa Einstein to Nathan, as well as some manuscripts, ephemera and photographs of Einstein.
Biographical Note
Albert Einstein was a professor of physics at the University of Zurich and the University of Berlin. From 1933 to his death in 1955 he was a professor at the Institute for Advanced Study at Princeton University.
Scope and Content Note
Composed mainly of correspondence between Einstein and the executor of his estate, Otto Nathan. A number of letters discuss the fate of Jews in Europe and other aspects of World War II. Others deal with Brandeis University, Jewish affairs in the United States, and personal matters. Also included are letters from Elsa Einstein to Nathan, as well as some manuscripts, ephemera, and photographs of Einstein.
Access
This collection is open for research according to the
regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library
without any additional restrictions.
Subject Headings
Names:
Beard, Charles A. (Charles Austin), 1874-1948; Nathan, Otto, 1893-1987; Freud, Sigmund, 1856-1939; Einstein, Elsa, 1876-1936; Frankfurter, Felix, 1882-1965
Organizations:
Brandeis University
Subjects:
Jews--Europe; Jews--United States; World War, 1939-1945; Intellectuals; Political refugees
Document Types:
Correspondence; Photographs
VCL Categories:
Politics; War and War Crimes
Encoding Information
Encoded by Elizabeth Clarke, December 2006. Updated by Emma Gronbeck, March 2023.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Morris and Adele Bergreen, 2003.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into 3 series and arranged chronologically within each of those series.
Series List
- Series I. Correspondence, 1934-1988; (Boxes 1-3)
- Series II. Manuscripts and Ephemera of Albert Einstein, 1930-1953; (Box 3)
- Series III. Photographs, 1919-1950; (Boxes 4-8)
Container List
- SERIES I. CORRESPONDENCE
  - Letters of Albert Einstein
    - Albert Einstein to Otto Nathan, [May 1934?]; (1 letter) (Folder 1.1)
    - Albert Einstein to Louis Brandeis, 29 May 1934; (1 letter) (Folder 1.2)
    - Albert Einstein to Otto Nathan, 21 Aug 1934; (1 letter) (Folder 1.3)
    - Albert Einstein to Otto Nathan, June 1935; (1 letter) (Folder 1.4)
    - Albert Einstein to Otto Nathan, 8 June [1935?]; (1 letter) (Folder 1.5)
    - Albert Einstein to Otto Nathan, 7 July 1935; (1 letter) (Folder 1.6)
    - Albert Einstein to Otto Nathan, 30 Jan 1936; (1 letter) (Folder 1.7)
    - Albert Einstein to Otto Nathan, 25 Feb 1936; (1 letter) (Folder 1.8)
    - Albert Einstein to "Dear Afterlife!", 4 May 1936; (1 letter) (Folder 1.9)
    - Albert Einstein to Otto Nathan, 7 May 1936; (1 letter) (Folder 1.10)
    - Albert Einstein to Otto Nathan, 7 July 1936; (1 letter) (Folder 1.11)
    - Albert Einstein to Otto Nathan, 14 July 1936; (1 letter) (Folder 1.12)
    - Albert Einstein to Otto Nathan, 22 July 1936; (1 letter) (Folder 1.13)
    - Albert Einstein to Otto Nathan, Sept 1936; (2 telegrams) (Folder 1.14)
    - Albert Einstein to Otto Nathan, 15 Sept 1936; (1 letter) (Folder 1.15)
    - Albert Einstein to Otto Nathan, [16 May 1937?]; (1 letter) (Folder 1.16)
    - Albert Einstein to Otto Nathan, 21 July 1937; (1 letter) (Folder 1.17)
    - Albert Einstein to Otto Nathan, 22 July 1937; (1 letter) (Folder 1.18)
    - Albert Einstein to Otto Nathan, written at the conclusion of a letter from Otto Nathan to Albert Einstein, [July 1937?]; (1 letter) (Folder 1.19)
    - Albert Einstein to Otto Nathan, 8 Nov 1937; (1 letter) (Folder 1.20)
    - Albert Einstein to Otto Nathan, 1 Dec 1937; (1 letter) (Folder 1.21)
    - Albert Einstein to Otto Nathan, 8 Apr [1938?]; (1 letter) (Folder 1.22)
    - Albert Einstein to Otto Nathan, 31 May 1938; (1 letter) (Folder 1.23)
    - Albert Einstein to Otto Nathan, 12 July 1938; (1 letter) (Folder 1.24)
    - Albert Einstein to Otto Nathan, 18 Sept 1938; (1 letter) (Folder 1.25)
    - Albert Einstein to Otto Nathan, 25 Oct 1938; (1 letter) (Folder 1.26)
    - Albert Einstein to Samuel Leidesdorf, 25 Oct 1938; (1 letter) (Folder 1.27)
    - Albert Einstein autograph draft unsigned On the recto of a sheet of autograph mathematical equations. At the bottom of the letter are notes meant for Otto Nathan and Herbert Maass, [1939?]; (1 letter) (Folder 1.28)
    - Albert Einstein to Otto Nathan, 17 Jan 1939; (1 letter) (Folder 1.29)
    - Albert Einstein to Otto Nathan Written at the bottom and side of a letter from Otto Nathan to Albert Einstein, [Feb 1939?]; (1 letter) (Folder 1.30)
    - Albert Einstein to Otto Nathan, 22 June 1939; (1 letter) (Folder 1.31)
    - Albert Einstein to Otto Nathan, [10 July 1939?]; (1 letter) (Folder 1.32)
    - Albert Einstein to Otto Nathan written at the bottom of the letter from Maass and Davidson, [August 1939?]; (1 letter) (Folder 1.33)
    - Albert Einstein to Otto Nathan, [5 Sept 1939?]; (1 letter) (Folder 1.34)
    - Albert Einstein to Otto Nathan, 23 Oct 1939; (1 letter) (Folder 1.35)
    - Albert Einstein to Otto Nathan, 29 Oct 1939; (1 letter) (Folder 1.36)
    - Albert Einstein to Otto Nathan, 3 Nov 1939; (1 letter) (Folder 1.37)
    - Albert Einstein to Otto Nathan, [24 Nov 1939?]; (1 letter) (Folder 1.38)
    - Albert Einstein to Helene Dukas, [Summer 1940?]; (1 letter) (Folder 1.39)
    - Albert Einstein to Otto Nathan, [10 Jan 1940?]; (1 letter) (Folder 1.40)
    - Albert Einstein to Helene Dukas, [9 May 1940?]; (1 letter) (Folder 1.41)
    - Albert Einstein to Otto Nathan, 7 July 1940; (1 letter) (Folder 1.42)
    - Albert Einstein to Otto Nathan, 30 July 1940; (1 letter) (Folder 1.43)
    - Albert Einstein to Otto Nathan, 31 July 1940; (1 letter) (Folder 1.44)
    - Albert Einstein to Otto Nathan, 7 Aug 1940; (1 letter) (Folder 1.45)
    - Albert Einstein to Otto Nathan, 14 Aug 1940; (1 letter) (Folder 1.46)
    - Albert Einstein to Otto Nathan, 16 Aug 1940; (1 letter) (Folder 1.47)
    - Albert Einstein to Otto Nathan, 23 Aug 1940; (1 letter) (Folder 1.48)
    - Albert Einstein to Otto Nathan, 19 Nov 1940; (1 letter) (Folder 1.49)
    - Albert Einstein to Otto Nathan, 2 May 1941; (1 letter) (Folder 1.50)
    - Albert Einstein to Otto Nathan, 14 Jan 1942; (1 letter) (Folder 1.51)
    - Albert Einstein to Otto Nathan, 26 Feb 1942; (1 letter) (Folder 1.52)
    - Albert Einstein to Otto Nathan, [2 Sept 1942?]; (1 item) (Folder 1.53)
    - Albert Einstein to Otto Nathan, 15 Dec 1942; (1 letter) (Folder 1.54)
    - Albert Einstein to Otto Nathan, 6 Feb 1943; (1 letter) (Folder 1.55)
    - Albert Einstein to Otto Nathan, 8 Mar 1945; (1 letter) (Folder 1.56)
    - Albert Einstein to Otto Nathan, 12 Nov 1945; (1 letter) (Folder 1.57)
    - Albert Einstein to Otto Nathan, [20 May 1946?]; (1 letter) (Folder 1.58)
    - Albert Einstein to Otto Nathan, [11 May 1947?]; (1 letter) (Folder 1.59)
    - Albert Einstein to Mr. Lazurs, 19 July 1947; (1 letter) (Folder 1.60)
    - Albert Einstein to Otto Nathan, 5 Oct 1947; (1 letter) (Folder 2.1)
    - Albert Einstein to Dr. Meili, 19 July 1948; (1 letter) (Folder 2.2)
    - Albert Einstein to Otto Nathan, [2 July 1948?]; (1 letter) (Folder 2.3)
    - Albert Einstein to Otto Nathan, 22 July 1948; (1 letter) (Folder 2.4)
    - Albert Einstein to Otto Nathan, [29 Aug 1948?]; (1 letter) (Folder 2.5)
    - Albert Einstein to Otto Nathan, 4 Sept 1948; (1 letter) (Folder 2.6)
    - Albert Einstein to Otto Nathan, 7 Oct 1948; (1 letter) (Folder 2.7)
    - Albert Einstein to Otto Nathan, [17 Feb 1949?]; (1 letter) (Folder 2.8)
    - Albert Einstein to Otto Nathan, 17 Feb 1949; (1 letter) (Folder 2.9)
    - Albert Einstein to Otto Nathan, 19 Feb 1949; (1 letter) (Folder 2.10)
    - Albert Einstein to Abram Sacher, 4 July 1949; (1 letter) (Folder 2.11)
    - Albert Einstein to Otto Nathan, 13 Aug 1949; (1 letter) (Folder 2.12)
    - Albert Einstein to Otto Nathan, 25 Jan 1950; (1 letter) (Folder 2.13)
    - Albert Einstein to Otto Nathan, 11 May 1950; (1 letter) (Folder 2.14)
    - Albert Einstein to Otto Nathan, 22 May 1953; (1 letter) (Folder 2.15)
    - Albert Einstein to Otto Nathan, 11 June [according to Nathan should be July] 1953; (1 letter) (Folder 2.16)
  - Letters of Otto Nathan
    - Otto Nathan to Elsa Einstein, 24 Sept 1934; (1 letter) (Folder 2.17)
    - Otto Nathan to Albert Einstein, 21 July 1936; (1 letter) (Folder 2.18)
    - Otto Nathan to Albert Einstein, 24 July 1936; (1 letter) (Folder 2.19)
    - Otto Nathan to B. Charney, 22 Mar 1937 Vladeck; (1 letter) (Folder 2.20)
    - Otto Nathan to Albert Einstein, 6 Apr 1937; (1 letter) (Folder 2.21)
    - Otto Nathan to David Niles, 10 Apr 1938; (1 letter) (Folder 2.22)
    - Otto Nathan to Miss Nike, 19 Apr 1938; (1 letter) (Folder 2.23)
    - Otto Nathan to Kurt Battsele, 19 Apr 1938; (1 letter) (Folder 2.24)
    - Otto Nathan to Lillie Schultz, 11 Sept 1938; (1 letter) (Folder 2.25)
    - Otto Nathan to Albert Einstein, 2 Oct 1938; (1 letter) (Folder 2.26)
    - Otto Nathan to Albert Einstein, 4 Nov 1938; (1 letter) (Folder 2.27)
    - Otto Nathan to Albert Einstein, 6 Nov 1938; (1 letter) (Folder 2.28)
    - Otto Nathan to Herbert Maass, 6 Nov 1938; (1 letter) (Folder 2.29)
    - Otto Nathan to Paul Guggenheim, 6 Nov 1938; (1 letter) (Folder 2.30)
    - Otto Nathan to Miss Nike, 6 Nov 1938; (1 letter) (Folder 2.31)
    - Otto Nathan to Mr. Lawson, 15 Dec 1938; (1 letter) (Folder 2.32)
    - Otto Nathan to Albert Einstein, 30 May 1939; (1 letter) (Folder 2.33)
    - Otto Nathan to Albert Einstein, 19 June 1939; (1 letter) (Folder 2.34)
    - Otto Nathan to Albert Einstein, 14 Nov 1940; (1 letter) (Folder 2.35)
    - Otto Nathan to Albert Einstein, 25 June 1947; (1 letter) (Folder 2.36)
    - Otto Nathan, signed "A.E." Richard Grossman. Likely Otto to Nathan's handwritten copy of a letter by Albert Einstein, 11 Aug 1947; (1 letter) (Folder 2.37)
    - Otto Nathan to the American Jewish Congress, 4 Nov 1947; (1 letter) (Folder 2.38)
    - Otto Nathan to Louise Waterman, 4 Nov 1947 Wise; (1 letter) (Folder 2.39)
    - Otto Nathan to Abram Sacher, 24 May 1949; (1 letter) (Folder 2.40)
    - Otto Nathan to Martin Blackman. With typed brochure titled "The Writings of Albert Einstein", 7 Feb 1975; (2 items) (Folder 2.41)
  - Letters of Elsa Einstein
    - Elsa Einstein to Otto Nathan, 25 Jan 1934; (1 letter) (Folder 3.1)
    - Elsa Einstein to Otto Nathan, [May or June 1934?]; (1 letter) (Folder 3.2)
    - Elsa Einstein to Otto Nathan, 1934; (1 letter) (Folder 3.3)
    - Elsa Einstein to Otto Nathan, 17 Sept 1934; (1 letter) (Folder 3.4)
    - Elsa Einstein to Otto Nathan, 20 Sept 1934; (1 letter) (Folder 3.5)
    - Elsa Einstein to Otto Nathan, 8 June 1935; (1 letter) (Folder 3.6)
    - Elsa Einstein to Otto Nathan, 17 July 1935; (1 letter) (Folder 3.7)
    - Elsa Einstein to Otto Nathan, 22 July 1935; (1 letter) (Folder 3.8)
    - Elsa Einstein to Otto Nathan, 24 July 1935; (1 letter) (Folder 3.9)
    - Elsa Einstein to Otto Nathan, 27 May 1936; (1 letter) (Folder 3.10)
    - Elsa Einstein to Otto Nathan, [10 Oct 1936?]; (1 letter) (Folder 3.11)
    - Elsa Einstein to Otto Nathan, 29 Nov [1936?]; (1 letter) (Folder 3.12)
  - Letters of Others
    - Felix Frankfurter to Albert Einstein, 25 May 1935; (1 letter) (Folder 3.13)
    - Sigmund Freud to Albert Einstein, 3 May 1936; (1 letter) (Folder 3.14)
    - Charles A. Beard to Albert Einstein, undated; (1 letter) (Folder 3.15)
    - Herbert Maass to Samuel Leidesdorf, 1 Nov 1938; (1 letter) (Folder 3.16)
    - David Levy to Otto Nathan, 10 Nov 1939; (1 letter) (Folder 3.17)
    - Frank Aydelotte to Albert Einstein, 3 Feb 1943; (1 letter) (Folder 3.18)
    - Michael Nisselson to Albert Einstein. In an initialed note below Einstein has written. "Not Answered A.E.,", 2 May 1953; (1 letter) (Folder 3.19)
    - Abram Sacher to Albert Einstein, 20 May 1953; (1 letter) (Folder 3.20)
    - Michael Gruning to The Einstein Archives, 18 May 1988; (1 letter) (Folder 3.21)
- SERIES II: MANUSCRIPTS AND EPHEMERA OF ALBERT EINSTEIN
  - Manuscripts (including typescripts)
    - Unsigned typescript for the "Labor/Chest May Day Demonstration", May 1936; (1 item) (Folder 3.22)
    - Typed, autographed manuscript signed. Concerning the National Council of Jewish Women ending with a call to help the Jewish people, 7 Jan 1938; (1 item) (Folder 3.23)
    - Typescript unsigned memorandum regarding Einstein's last will, 9 Mar 1940; (1 item) (Folder 3.24)
    - Twelve line poem written in honor of Helene Dukas, 3 Aug 1942; (1 item) (Folder 3.25)
    - Twenty-eight-line poem for Emmanuel Libman, [Oct 1942?]; (1 item) (Folder 3.26)
    - Twenty line birthday poem possibly for Otto Nathan, 14 July 1943; (1 letter) (Folder 3.27)
    - Typescript [Apparently for The National Wartime Conference on May 1944], (1 item) (Folder 3.28)
    - Statement regarding George Alpert and Brandeis University's Board of Trustees, 25 July 1947; (1 item) (Folder 3.29)
    - Typescript regarding U.S. relations with Russia, [27 May 1948?]; (1 item) (Folder 3.30)
    - English translation of typescript regarding U.S. relations with Russia, 1 June 1948; (1 item) (Folder 3.31)
    - Typescript on the subject of war atomic weapons and politics, [10 June 1948?]; (1 item) (Folder 3.32)
    - Manuscript discussing war, politics, world cooperation, etc., [July 1948?]; (1 item) (Folder 3.33)
    - Typescript, regarding Greenglass' fallibility as a witness and two points where the Rosenbergs could be found to have acted suspiciously, 23 Mar 1952; (1 item) (Folder 3.34)
    - Typescript concerning the breakdown of collective security, undated; (1 item) (Folder 3.35)
    - Unsigned manuscript probably pre-World War II, undated; (1 item) (Folder 3.36)
  - Ephemera
    - A page removed from a calendar to note the book belongs to Otto Nathan and in the case of an accident Einstein should be contacted, [end of Dec 1941?]; (1 item) (Folder 3.37)
    - Five checks signed in full by Albert Einstein, 1947-1953; (5 items) (Folder 3.38)
    - Albert Einstein and Henry Wallace signed petition, [1950?]; (1 item) (Folder 3.39)
    - Albert Einstein's pocket calendar for 1930, (1 item) (Folder 3.40)
- SERIES III. PHOTOGRAPHS
  - Signed Photographs
    - Albert Einstein in a v-neck sweater, 17 Oct 1928; (1 item) (Folder 7.1)
    - Five mounted photographs of Albert Einstein, 1935; (1 item) (Folder 4.1)
    - Albert Einstein at the tiller of a sailboat, framed, 1936; (1 item) (Folder 5.1)
    - Albert Einstein looking directly into the camera, undated; (1 item) (Folder 6.1)
  - Unsigned Photographs
    - Albert Einstein in jacket and tie looking to his left above his glasses, framed, undated; (1 item) (Folder 4.2)
    - Albert Einstein in 3/4 profile looking directly into camera, undated; (1 item) (Folder 6.2)
    - Albert Einstein shown in 3/4 profile with pen clip showing on the collar of his sweatshirt, undated; (1 item) (Folder 6.3)
    - Albert Einstein seated wearing a sweater with his head slightly raised in profile, undated; (1 item) (Folder 6.4)
    - Albert Einstein sitting wearing a wing-tip collared shirt, 1919; (1 item) (Folder 7.2)
    - Albert Einstein and his wife, Tokyo, Nov 1922; (1 item) (Folder 7.3)
    - Albert Einstein and Charles St. John with St. John's spectrographic apparatus, 1931; (1 item) (Folder 7.4)
    - 'Albert Einstein' by Joseph Scharl, Oil painting on burlap 1/2 portrait of Albert Einstein, 1950; (1 item) (Folder 7.5)
    - 'Professor Einstein' by S. Elfinger, charcoal drawing of Albert Einstein's head, [1954?]; (1 item) (Folder 7.6)
    - Albert Einstein and Otto Nathan walking in garden, undated; (1 item) (Folder 7.7)
    - Albert Einstein smoking in garden with Otto Nathan, undated; (1 item) (Folder 7.8)
    - Albert Einstein smoking in garden with Otto Nathan, undated; (1 framed item) (Box 8)
    - Albert Einstein on a porch wearing fuzzy slippers, undated; (1 item) (Folder 7.9)
    - A youthful picture of Albert Einstein with his sister Maja, undated; (1 item) (Folder 7.10)
    - Albert Einstein seated with four other gentlemen, undated; (1 item) (Folder 7.11)
    - Sculpture of Albert Einstein's hands, undated; (1 item) (Folder 7.12)
    - Profile of sculpture of Albert Einstein's head, undated; (1 item) (Folder 7.13)
    - "Albert Einstein" by Jo Davidson, terra cotta bust of Albert Einstein, undated; (1 item) (Folder 7.14)
    - Profile of sculpture of Albert Einstein's Head with artist, undated; (1 item) (Folder 7.15)